Um yeah, we have um so yeah um the the
person is dead here.
>> Okay, get me the address, please.
>> Okay. Okay, I'm working on it.
>> Concentrate on that.
>> And the people are just distraught.
>> I understand that they are distraught,
but
>> I'm working on it. I'm working on it.
Paisley Park. We're at Paisley Park.
>> You're at Paisley Park. Okay. That's in
Trenhassen. Are you with the person
who's
>> Yes, it's Prince.
>> And CNN has now confirmed that the
artist Prince is dead.
>> He was found in [music] his elevator
unresponsive
in his compound uh Paisley [music] Park
in Minneapolis. the the number of songs,
seventime Grammy winner, 30 nominations,
the number [music] of songs that have
touched people's lives throughout uh his
entire career. Uh this [music] is going
to be very very hard news to take.
In recent times, music lovers have been
confounded with the tragic and shocking
[music] news that some of their most
beloved stars had passed away in
controversial circumstances.
The music world has again been stunned
by the sudden [music] and tragic news
that Prince, the legendary musician,
died at his home in [music] Minneapolis
at the age of just 57.
He was supposed to live till he was in
his 90s, you know, doing concerts and
joy. I mean, he just is all about joy
and he brings so much joy to so many
people. He
loved to
connect with you through the music. I
mean, the Prince fans, the all of the
Prince fans, they know what I'm talking
about. Everybody feels like they have.
If you are a Prince fan, you feel like
he has spoken to you.
>> He's known worldwide, [music] but he is
a motan, and we're all from Minnesota.
And when you lose one of our own, just
like Kirby Pucket, you you got to show
up and show respect. He put everything
he had [music] into the music.
Everything. I mean, he lived at his
studio. So, I mean, he [music] just put
everything that he had into it. And he
took stories from people's lives, from
his own experiences in life, [music] and
put it into his music. And I think
that's why the world just related to
him, not so much as just a black artist,
but as an artist in general. I mean, he
had one of the I mean, this is the most
you you see all these people together
and they are all united together to come
pay their respects. I think the world's
going to take a break from all the stuff
that's been going on and just remember
somebody that deserves it and has been
there for everybody. I mean, he did a
lot of children's events, a lot of, you
know, disability events [music] and, you
know, he just put everything back into
the community. He used to just pop up at
the Chanhasson Theater and he would pop
up at the McDonald's. He loved
McDonald's. So, I think um just a little
break for everybody [music] for all the
hate that's out there right now to just
reflect on this time.
[music]
They responded to Paisley Park uh to
look for him and found him unresponsive
in the elevator. We have no reason to
believe at this point that this was a
suicide, but again, this is early on in
this investigation and uh it's
continuing to uh we'll continue to
investigate.
>> We received the call at 10:12 yesterday
morning to come and assist the Carver
County Sheriff's Office in this
investigation. Our chief medical
examiner arrived on the scene at 11:30
yesterday morning local time and was on
the scene for several hours. The autopsy
this morning began at 9:00 a.m. Central
Daylight Time and concluded at 100 p.m.
And just shortly, I received word that
his body did leave Midwest Medical
Examiner's Office and was released to
the family.
>> Just days [music] before his death,
Prince's private jet made an emergency
landing in Illinois due to him suddenly
becoming [music] ill. An audio recording
of the pilot requesting an emergency
landing reports an unresponsive
passenger. What's the nature of the
emergency? What's the nature of the an
unresponsive passenger? Was it a male or
female passenger?
>> The musician [music] was transported to
hospital where he was given a so-called
safe shot of Narcan, an antidote often
used in suspected drug overdoses.
[music] It was reported that doctors
urged Prince to stay in hospital for at
least 24 hours, but Prince [music]
checked himself out after just 3 hours.
Authorities confirmed that the star was
last seen alive at 8:00 p.m. on
Wednesday night, an hour after he was
pictured at a pharmacy near his home.
>> In addition [music] to all of the
reports about Prince's clean living, his
veganism, his Jehovah's Witness [music]
beliefs, there are also a wide array of
reports about his opiate addiction,
about his love of pills, and some of the
less kind of clean living uh things that
may have happened towards [music] the
end of his life and in fact contributed
to his death.
>> Dr. D who claims to be Prince is a drug
dealer and again we don't know whether
this is the case or not said that he
never met anybody who suffered as much
stage fright as Prince and this ties in
[music] to the narcissism that was at
the heart of his personality. The man
who on the one hand has to be bigger,
greater [music] and grander than the
rest carries that private vulnerability,
that naked [music] raw insecurity
which is part of the drive that makes
him perform. The man who on the one hand
is too frightened to go on stage yet
when he's on stage he's too obsessive,
too driven to come off it. That
combination [music] is toxic as well as
responsible for the work of so many
[music] great artists. And perhaps
that's what artists like Prince that's
the price they pay for the creativity.
It's the it's the [music] Fouian pact if
you want that they make. Give me my
creativity.
Give me my [music] art and I will give
you my life.
On June 3rd, 2016, it was confirmed that
Prince's death was a result of an
accidental overdose of the painkiller
Fentanel. The report from the Midwest
[music]
Medical Examiner's Office in Minnesota
came more than a month after the singer
was found dead in a lift at his home.
According to the autopsy report, Prince
self-administered fentanyl, an opioid
many times more powerful than heroin. In
the weeks following his death,
investigators had been looking into
whether Prince had a prescription drug
problem. This surprised Prince's close
friends and family, who stated that
Prince avoided alcohol and drugs and
maintained a healthy lifestyle. However,
Prince's team had been organizing
treatment with a California addiction
[music] doctor to help him kick an
addiction to painkillers. According to a
search warrant obtained by news [music]
agencies, the day before Prince's death,
a local doctor treated him for fatigue
and [music] anemia, stemming from
apparent opioid withdrawal. For weeks,
the world media speculated about the
cause of Prince's death. [music] Now
that we know the truth, Prince's musical
legacy can live on without being
shrouded in the mystery of his sudden
passing.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Prince was one of the most naturally
gifted artists of all time and also one
of the most mysterious. This man is one
of the most committed [music] artists
I've ever known. And by that I mean
committed to music utterly. And he was
able to do almost everything.
>> In the 80s, at a time when other mega
stars such as Michael Jackson, Bruce
[music] Springsteen, and Madonna were
delivering an album every 3 years or so,
[music] Prince remained prolific to an
almost inhuman degree.
>> To say that he was prolific [music]
would be an understatement. His genius
was unrestrained. It was unstoppable.
>> He wrote his first song when he was, I
think, seven years [music] old. And he
went on to sell over a 100 million
albums, 100 million mile albums. He
become one of the most iconic artists
[music] of all time. He contributed to
fashion. He contributed to film. He
contributed to music. But the one
constant in his life that sustained him
and sustained his creativity was his
work ethic. A byproduct of his
inexhaustible output was Prince's
[music] tendency toward weward,
self-indulgent career moves that
sometimes alienated even his most
[music] ardent supporters. His influence
is unparalleled, and his legacy will
live on through his inspirational music.
>> One of Prince's greatest talents [music]
as an artist was to connect, to engage,
to compel. People couldn't look away
from his music. In this fascinating
documentary, we take an in-depth look
into the life and times of one of
music's greatest performers, Prince.
In a 1999 BET [music] Tonight interview,
uh, Prince, you know, famously said that
that he got into music and and he and
[music] he got into doing what he do
what he does, uh, because just cuz he
loved playing, [music] you know, jumping
off pianos, as he says in the interview.
>> You still like going out doing dates?
>> Oh, man. That's that's my life. Uh, I
got into the music business because I
loved playing so much.
>> Um, you don't really get [music] into
the business to be a star. or at least I
didn't. I didn't get in to make a whole
bunch of money or anything like that or
meet a whole bunch of women. Just so
happens those are the things that came
along with it. But uh um I was always um
playing a lot and uh
it's what it's all about, jumping off
pianos. That's
>> it's all about jumping off pianos and
hurting your foot when you jump.
>> The sense you get from him is that and
these are his his words, you know, the
art came first. the money and the women
[music] came after. And that again keys
into a number of things, not least of
which was his work ethic. The world is
full of people who want the world and
they want it now. [music] They want the
money, they want the women, they want
the sex, they want the fame, they want
the adoration, but they don't put the
time or the effort. And they don't have
the kind of intense passion for their
[music] art that Prince did. And it's
that line that separates
genius, if you want, those who go on to
become
artists of the caliber of Prince, and
there's not many of them around. Prince,
you know, is in a very small, thin group
of the most iconic figures of 20th and
21st century art.
Prince arrived on the scene in the
late7s, and it didn't take long for him
to upend the music world with his
startling music and arresting demeanor.
He rewrote the rule [music] book,
forging a synthesis of black funk and
white rock that served as a blueprint
for cuttingedge [music] music in the
80s. Prince made dance music that rocked
and rock music that had a bristling
funky backbone.
>> One of the things that Prince will
always [music] be remembered for is the
way that he could change genre of music
[music] absolutely fluently, whether it
was pop or rock or funk or R&B. And he
didn't just do it album to album. He
would change completely the style of
music from song to song on an album. So
what was so revolutionary about this man
is that he was completely fluent across
a wide range of styles of music and he
loved to [music] fuse them together in
different ways and experiment in a way
that no one really did that [music] to
that degree before or since.
>> From the beginning, Prince and his music
were androgynous, sexy, and provocative.
His colorful image and revolutionary
music made Prince a figure comparable in
paradigmshifting impact to Little
Richard, James Brown, and Jimmyi [music]
Hendris. Not only did he release a
series of groundbreaking albums, he
toured frequently, produced [music]
albums, and wrote songs for many other
artists, and recorded hundreds of songs
that still lie unreleased in [music] his
vaults. With each album he released,
Prince showed remarkable stylistic
growth and musical diversity, constantly
experimenting with different sounds,
textures, [music] and genres.
Occasionally, his music was
inconsistent, in part because of his
eclecticism, [music]
but his experiments frequently
succeeded. No other contemporary [music]
artist blended so many diverse styles
into a cohesive hole. Purple Rain around
the world in a day. Batman and Diamonds
and Pearls have [music] sold more than 2
million copies a piece. Purple Rain
alone sold 13 million copies and topped
the album charts for nearly half a year
at the height of Prince's reign in the
mid80s.
>> When you think about Prince, [music] you
really kind of imagine what you see in
the video for Purple Rain. First of all,
he's in purple. He's on stage. He's
[music] performing. He's a superstar.
and he's putting out this very sexy,
powerful stage presence. [music] Despite
the fact that he's not a very big guy,
he has a very big presence and and when
he's on stage, he looks like a very
large individual. And I think what you
see in Purple [music] Rain is kind of uh
scenes from the film, the very famous
film of course called Purple Rain
[music] kind of weaved throughout the
video. The story here is about a
performer, a guy that fronts a band who
gets up on stage and sings who has a
very complicated personal life. It's
[music] dark. It's not exactly a happy
uh song, but there's a lot of overtures
of this kind of gothic romanticism that
we see from Prince [music] throughout
his career.
[music]
>> [music]
>> I think purple rain is an incredible
song. It's an anthem of sorts and
[music] you know there's a lot of
apocryphal imagery. Prince was asked
about it many times and he did have a
real fascination at the [music] time
about the apocalypse and the end of the
world and purple [music] rain is really
about when the sky turned red and blue
and rained purple and it's the end of
the world and it's being with the person
you love and your god at that time.
That's what Prince [music] is basically
alluded to later in life. As Rolling
Stone contended in 1989, perhaps more
than any other artist, Prince called the
tune for pop music in [music] the 80s,
imprinting his Minneapolis sound on an
entire generation of musicians, both
black and white.
The product of a broken home, Prince
found refuge in music.
>> I was I was leaving school and I looked
down and I seen this guy go in front of
me and he was a shorter type guy. I
didn't know. Then down the line I
figured out [music] and we used to call
him Skipper. That was the only name I
knew him by until after he [music] made
his album. The one time I I really
noticed was that when I I [music] would
always see Prince playing the keyboard,
right? And I thought he was a
keyboardist, right? And all of a sudden
he got off the keyboard [music] and sat
on the side of the stage and started
playing Carlos Santana. That's the first
time I ever heard him play the guitar.
And it was masterful.
By his early teens, he'd mastered
multiple instruments and was fronting
his first band, Grand Central. A demo
tape by the Young Prodigy resulted in
major label interest and an 18-year-old
Prince signed to Warner Brothers
insisting on the right to self-produce
his music.
>> He was brought to the attention of
Warner Brothers Records by a local
Warner Brothers representative who said,
"We have this fantastic kid in Minnesota
and you've really got to hear him." They
signed him up and they said, "And we
[music] think he's so good, we're going
to have him work with Maurice White."
They recommended that he work with
Maurice White, the recently deceased
Eminence of Earth, Wind, and [music]
Fire. Now, in the late 1970s, you
couldn't get a hotter producer than
Maurice White, unless it was Barry Gibb.
It was a complete [music] surprise that
Prince said, "No, I'm going to do
myself." And and he
did all the instruments himself.
So even from the ages of 17 and 18, he
was completely determined to be in
charge of his own career.
>> Prince released his first album for you
in April 1978. To minimal fanfare, Soft
and Wet introduced his erotic approach
while I Want to Be Your Lover and Why
You Want to Treat Me So Bad from
subsequent albums. Prince suggested his
musical range and significantly upped
his profile. Interest in the youthful
star was further kindled by Dirty Mind,
a provocative and sineuously funky album
that appeared like a directional marker
at the start of the 80s. The jittery new
wavish When You Were Mine became a club
hit, yet Dirty Mind largely proved too
hot to handle for the radio.
The
>> Dirty Mind album was quite unfit for
radio airplay
for princely reasons. you can imagine.
Although uh When You Were Mine was a
great song which [music] has become a
standard of sorts recorded by various
artists including Cindy Looper. And we
really didn't know if he was going to
put it back on the rails until
controversy came out. Now, [music] at
this point, this was four albums in four
years, and this was the pace at which he
was going to continue throughout the
1980s.
>> Prince's breakthrough was 1999. a
self-produced double [music] album made
at his home studio. He'd toned down, if
not entirely tamed, the hardcore
sexuality, and the longish dancable
tracks appealed to disco and the new
wave fans alike. Whereas many saw
divisions in culture in terms of
everything from musical preferences to
skin color, Prince formed a party-minded
unity around the various audienc's
shared interests in dance, music, sex,
and romance. Those were the priorities
outlined in DMSR, one of 1999's key
tracks. [music] The album launched three
major singles, Little Red Corvette,
Delirious, [music] and 1999.
>> 1999 may be called 1999, [music]
but this is a quintessential 1980s music
video. Everybody has big hair. Everybody
seems [music] to have a perm. You've got
a lot of um the kind of one-handed
gloves and the hat and the asymmetric
hairstyle and all the other things that
you [music] associate with 1980s. It has
the feel of a 1980s song and has very
[music] much the look of a 1980s song.
You see Prince on stage with his band
performing and this is all about
highlighting his concert presence, his
stage presence and showing that he knows
how to have a good time.
[music]
Tonight I'm going to party [music] like
it's 1999.
>> He was very much a trailblazer in so
many respects. His video for Little Red
Corvette for instance that you know
along with Michael Jackson's Billy Jean
paved the way for black artist to be
represented on MTV where he could
innovate. He would always just want to
push the boundaries and that's the sign
of a great artist.
baby.
[music]
>> One of the defining releases of the 80s
along with Michael Jackson's Thriller
and Bruce Springsteen's Born in the USA,
1984's Purple Rain elevated Prince from
cult hero to superstar. The movie,
loosely based on his life story, was set
in Minneapolis and his real life
hangout, The First Avenue and the
Seventh Street Entry Club. Prince wrote
the treatment and played the lead role.
The film grossed $80 million, and the
album, which won Prince an Oscar for
best soundtrack, reigned hits for a
year. Purple Rain, Let's Go Crazy, and
When Doves Cry being the standout
tracks. In When Dove's Cry, the video
opens [music] with Prince naked in a
bathtub. And it's a bit of a startling
image [music] because of how feminine he
looks, but at the same time, he has this
very masculine, sexy energy. He gets out
of the bathtub, and we see [music] this
kind of revealing shot of his washboard
abs, and he kind of crawls across the
floor in this very naked feline way.
[music]
The sweat of your body,
my
picture.
>> It's really interesting to watch this
video because you see Prince and clips
of Purple Rain where he's this rockar
with this very troubled home life. You
see him on stage and then you see him
rushing home where his stepfather is
abusing his mother and he has to kind of
pull him off his mom.
[music]
[singing]
>> Why do we scream at each other?
[music]
>> It puts Prince out there as a leading
man, but it's also a very sexual way to
start the video. We didn't see a lot of
musicians, male musicians at this time,
[music] putting themselves in out there
in this way, like to start out naked in
a bathtub. Um, but that's really very
much a part of the hypersexualized image
that [music] Prince was already putting
out there. In the video for Let's Go
Crazy, it's quintessential Prince.
You've got him on stage in tight
trousers and a ruffle blouse with a high
neck performing with a guitar and
looking very sexual and in control.
interspersed in the video. You have
scenes from Purple Rain, sex scenes with
the beautiful Appalonia showing her her
her courtship and seduction [music] by
Prince and also some of the scenes of
his very troubled home life. Let's go.
>> It's a it's it's a long music video and
it feels very much like an advertisement
or trailer for the film.
>> [music]
>> For any other artist, Purple Rain would
have been a hard act to follow. But
Prince already had another album in the
works. Around the World in a Day, a
Tuitive Force of Psychedelic Soul
released in 1985, it became his second
consecutive number one album and the
first to appear on his own Paisley Park
label. [music] With Prince Mania in full
effect, the album generated two more top
10 hits, Raspberry Beret and Pop Life.
Even a bad film, Under the Cherry Moon,
Prince's first real miscue, couldn't
halt his momentum, as the accompanying
soundtrack, Parade, included the classic
Kiss, his third number one single.
>> In the video for Kiss, we see Prince in
this [music] very sexy two-piece outfit.
The top almost looks like a woman's uh
exercise midrift [music]
top, and he's wearing like black her
leggings. It's a very feminine,
androgynous look for Prince.
>> [music]
>> A lot [music] of Prince's um breaking
down of barriers had to do with the way
that he [music] was appearing to be two
genders at the same time. And in this
video, we see him in a way kind of
prancing around as if he's a very sexy
woman in heels, bearing [music] her
midf, but at the same time, he's a very
much a man who is masculine, who's
[music] sexual, and who wants a woman.
So, it's an interesting combination, and
it's it's a motif that Prince would play
with throughout his career, including
ultimately wanting to be called a symbol
[music] that was both male and female.
rich to be my girl. You don't have to be
cool to rule my world. Ain't no
particular sign.
I just want you extra time in your
>> Prince hit an artistic peak with Sign of
the Times in 1987. Sign of the Times was
Prince's most musically expansive and
lyrically incisive album. Sign of the
Times was the first pop [music] hit to
make reference to AIDS, the disease of
the 1980s.
And he even recorded it first a year
before it came out. But
uh even [music] after that year's
weight, which nobody knew was a weight,
it still was a breakthrough. That's how
ahead of the of the times he was. On the
sobering sign of the times, Prince
enumerated a catalog of social ills over
a skeletal funk track. Other hits of the
album included You Got the Look, a duet
with Sheena Eastston, and I Could Never
Take the Place of Your Man. Around this
time, Prince talked of dueling
identities within himself, conjuring
characters that represented his good
side, Camille, and dark side, Spooky
Electric. The latter had its say on the
Black Album, a controversial hardcore
set that was aborted shortly before its
intended release. In its place came Love
Sexy, which contained the terrific
Alphabet Street. Commercially, Prince
found himself back on top in 1989 with
his soundtrack to the first Batman
movie. Prince's dense, tangled funk
meshed with film producer Tim Burton's
dark gothic vision and resulted in the
album Batman and single Bat Dance
shooting to the top of the charts. That
was so audacious when you think about
it. Uh [music] Tim Burton
with that film, a giving Jack Nicholson
basically co-lead as the Joker, but B
just saying to Prince, "Give me a
soundtrack." And it was fantastic.
Number one single, That Dance.
>> A year later, Prince made another of his
own movies, Graffiti Bridge. Although it
was panned, the double album soundtrack
was compelling, particularly the
impassioned Thieves in the Temple. In
the early 90s, Prince assembled a
backing band, The New Power Generation.
They debuted on Diamonds and Pearls,
Prince's most accessible and hitfilled
[music] album since Purple Rain.
Everything about it was elaborately
conceived, including the holographic
cover. The album returned Prince to
radio with a string of funky upbeat
hits. Get Off, Diamond and Pearls, Money
Don't Matter, Tonight, and Cream.
>> The video for Cream is about as sexy as
you would think it would be [music] when
it comes to the name of the song and the
kind of performer that Prince is. You
see him dressed in his full ruffle neck
blouse [music] and his tight pants and
high heels, gyating on the stage with
very scantily clad women in kind of like
bodysuits. At [music] one point he's
humping the stage. He's prancing around.
And it's a very hypersexual song.
[music]
>> [music]
>> The lyrics are sexual, the video is
sexual, and it's a celebration really of
the naughty side of Prince that people
really kept coming back for.
>> Diamond and Pearls would turn out to be
Prince's biggest album of the '90s. It
was followed in 1992 by an album that
marked the first appearance of the
symbol that Prince would formally adopt
a year later as his name. Ironically,
the disc whose title was a symbol and
therefore referred to as the love symbol
album opened with a song called My Name
is Prince. [music] The numerology minded
7 peaked at number seven. But Prince's
most infectious funk workout, Sexy MF,
proved too profane for radio. Still,
Prince seemed to be on a roll. [music]
In August 1992, he signed a contract
extension with Warner Brothers for six
more albums, and he acquired the title
of vice president with the label.
However, by the mid9s, [music] relations
would sour as he began appearing in
public with the word slave scrolled on
his face while agitating [music] to get
off the label. In a 1999 uh bet tonight
interview, uh Prince talked about
perhaps one of the most controversial
things that [music] he did was was to
change his name from Prince to the
artist formerly [music] known as Prince
or the artist or and he created a love
symbol to to represent that. And
what was fascinating about what he said
was and controversial about what he said
was he described himself as a slave. And
he makes it clear [music] he's not
talking about the kind of slavery that
African-Americans had to endure [music]
when they first came to the to to
America. That's not the kind of slavery
he's talking about. He says yes. He says
it's relative.
>> Prince was in a trap. Prince was under
contract to Prince was owned.
>> You know, um I can't use Purple Rain. I
can't use this song. I can't sell the
song Purple Rain now unless I record it
again, which I have plans to do if I
can't in fact get the master recording
that I believe is uh one of my children,
you know. So, um uh I did I had to get
freed from the uh the mentality of being
a slave, you understand? Okay. And
that's not to equate myself with the
same u situations that we suffered
coming to this country. But you know
everything is relative. If you are
owned, you are owned. If you can't do
everything that you want to do, if there
is a ceiling and you're not allowed to
go as high as you can go, you are in
fact a slave.
>> Rather tellingly, he says, "If you're
owned, you're owned. And if you can't do
everything you want to do, then you're a
slave." And that sums up both Prince's
desire to control his own destiny and
his obsessive
compulsion to be the best possible
artist that he could be which is that
kind of rare drive that only artists of
the caliber of Prince and only an artist
like Prince could do. That is what made
him what he is.
In 1993, Prince launched an independent
label, NPG Records, [music] with a
various artists compilation, 1 800 New
Funk. His next single, The Most [music]
Beautiful Girl in the World, which also
appeared on NPG, marked a return to
hitmaking form.
>> Prince's video for The Most Beautiful
Girl in the World, is one of his most
romantic videos that he made in his
career. It was the first song released
on the album right after he changed his
name to a symbol and it was a it was a
different kind of prince than we were
used to seeing because this was a prince
who was very much in love. He this the
woman who inspired the song was his then
fiance [music] Matei Garcia who he ended
up marrying shortly after he shot the
video on Valentine's Day. [music] The
video is all about marriage. There's a
beautiful bride and Prince is standing
there looking quite regal in red and
he's singing about this woman who is the
most beautiful girl in the world. You
[music] don't see Prince gyating,
humping, getting naked, other things
that you see on Prince videos. This
video is romantic. It's a celebration of
love and it very much reflects the state
of mind that Prince was in himself
[music]
when he made this song. Could you be
the most beautiful [music] girl in the
world?
It's plain to [music] see.
You're the reason that God made a girl.
[music]
Meanwhile, relations with Warner
Brothers, to which he was still
contracted, were deteriorating badly.
The release of the Gold Experience was
delayed while he argued with the label.
Disenchanted with what he saw as an
unfairly one-sided relationship between
label and artist that rendered the
latter a slave, Prince was let out of
his contract with Warner Brothers in
1996. [music]
His last album of new music for the
label was Chaos and Disorder. After
being liberated from his former label,
he quickly resumed his prolific ways.
Distributed [music] through a special
arrangement with Arista, Brave Unto the
Joy Fantastic gave Prince the best of
both worlds, artistic ownership of his
work, and major label distribution.
[music] The album was notable for its
production credit, Prince, which marked
the first time he'd reverted to his old
name in 6 years. In February 2004,
Prince appeared with Beyonce at the
Grammy Awards, playing his own Purple
Rain, [music]
Let's Go Crazy, and Baby I'm a Star
along with Beyonce's Crazy in Love. A
month later, he was inducted into the
Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. During the
closing ceremony, he played the song
ending solo on George Harrison's While
My Guitar Gently Weeps, wowing the
assembly with his ferocious virtuosity.
and they are doing while my guitar
gently weeps. And uh for the first three
minutes or so,
Tom Petty and Jeff Lynn are training
lead vocals. And it's one of those usual
superstar jams. And [music] then Prince
has a minute long guitar piece
and he tears the roof off the sucker and
and there he is with all these famous
people on stage and he is stealing the
show completely and at the conclusion of
his solo he throws his guitar in the air
and in the clip you don't see the guitar
come down but from the ey line you see
that he's just looking to make sure that
his roies caught the thing [music]
and then he walks off stage with
the gate and look of well I've now done
what I came into this world to do
[snorts]
[laughter] and and and leaves
[music]
that you
Still [music] my [singing]
Chevy.
[music]
[applause and cheering]
Together,
these performances made Prince the talk
of pop music again. Something similar
would occur when he played the 2007
Super Bowl halftime show.
>> Prince's Super Bowl performance in 2007
is widely [music] believed to be the
best and greatest Super Bowl performance
of all time. Critics [music] absolutely
were blown away by his stage presence
and the magnificence of his [music]
performance. You have to picture the
scene. It's in Miami and it is pouring
rain. It's one of the only times it has
poured rain at halftime in the Super
Bowl in history, if not the only time.
>> Beloved,
we are gathered here to get through this
thing called life. Another thing he did
which was extraordinary was to cover
other songs during the performance.
Mostly when Super Bowl artists are asked
to perform, they do their own music and
that's maybe they invite a guest singer
to come in and do a song like we saw
with Coldplay and Beyonce, but generally
they do their own songs. What Prince did
was to cover other songs such as Jimmyi
Hendricks and the Foo Fighters in the
midst of this incredible performance of
his own hits.
[music]
my
new [music]
>> and everyone was incredibly excited to
see Prince show up standing outside
getting completely soaked and yet didn't
take away an ounce from the highpowered
energy and and sheer amazingness of his
performance.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I think what Prince very in a very savvy
way did here was to give the public what
he knew they wanted was a rip roaring
good time full of high energy and music
that they loved. [music]
>> [cheering]
[music]
>> From mid 2010 through the end of 2012,
Prince toured throughout Europe,
America, Europe again, Canada, and
Australia. During 2013, he released
several singles, starting with
Screwdriver and continuing with
Breakfast Can Wait in the summer of that
year. All this activity was a prelude to
the spring announcement that Prince had
resigned to Warner Brothers, the label
he had feuded with 20 years prior. As
part of the deal, he wound up receiving
the ownership of his master recording,
and the label planned a reissue campaign
that would begin with an expanded
reissue of Purple Rain, roughly timed to
celebrate its 30th anniversary.
>> In the same way [music] that Prince is
hard to pin down when it comes to one
musical genre type, Prince was very much
an enigma across his entire [music]
career. He refused to be pinned down
even in terms of gender. Was he male?
Was he female? [music] Was he gay? Was
he straight? Was he black? lessy white.
He was He was definitely black, but in
some of his videos, he has so much face
powder on. [music] He looks completely
white. His style of dressing, it's it's
masculine, but it's super feminine. His
sexuality was very much a [music] male
predator who was going to seduce a young
woman, but he was also hyper feminine.
Prince was an enigma in that you
couldn't [music] really put your finger
on who and what he was, and that was
part of his [music] appeal. There's a
wonderful anecdote which was narrated by
Prince's publicist and they say that
after a performance he would make the
band watch a [music] video of the show
they'd just performed. So it all sit sit
backstage and every time he spotted a
bum note he would berate the person who
did it. That is what [music] it meant to
work for Prince. And whereas at times it
could and was undoubtedly overbearing
and relentless. That's just how you get
better at stuff. And that's why Prince
was an inspiration. You know, [music]
artists like that don't just happen
overnight. They have to work at it. And
that anecdote really sums up that
obsessive [music]
driven desire to just reach a pinnacle
of creative achievement that no other
artist had ever done. And you have to
have that dynamic going on [music] to
perform as beautifully and to create as
prolifically as an artist like Prince
because there's one fact about
perfectionists
and narcissists but particularly true of
perfectionists and the two are very
closely linked is that they can't
[music] they can't ever be good enough.
If you're a perfectionist you never
reach perfection and you're always
striving to do it. You want more and
more and [music] more and more. Let's
just make this right. Let's just make
this right. But it's never good enough.
You've always got to improve. And it's
that narcissism, that perfectionism, and
that incredible creative drive and work
ethic that goes to make a genius like
Prince.
>> Since Prince's death, worldwide press
have rapsided about Prince's
otherworldly talents and profound impact
on pop music.
>> Here's a person who combined [music] uh
elements of James Brown with Jimmyi
Hendris and did it at the highest level
of the world. and then in the meantime
was also controlling [music] every
single element of production of his
music.
>> To sum up, Prince's legacy would be
about his sheer raw talent. a guy who
could play every single instrument on
every single track on every album who
released 39 albums in his career and
left thousands of songs [music] in a
vault in his home on his death. I get
the impression that no [music] one need
worry that they did not get the best of
Prince because the best of Prince it
would appear to me was not what he held
back but what he gave out. So in fact we
all got the best of Prince.
the seven Grammys, the Golden Globe, the
Academy Award, the virtuosic mastery of
every instrument he encountered, the
mythic persona he cultivated, the
singular and revolutionary artistic
vision he possessed that transcended
race, culture, [music] and sex. They the
legendary parts that composed Prince, an
unparalleled force who was taken too
soon, but whose work [music] will
radiate into eternity.
>> [music]